The Life, Love and Genius of Brian Wilson
Love & Mercy is a drama, music, history film directed by Bill Pohlad.
In the late 1960s, the Beach Boys' Brian Wilson stops touring, produces
"Pet Sounds" and begins to lose his grip on reality.
By the 1980s, under the sway of a controlling therapist,
he finds a savior in Melinda Ledbetter.
Brian Wilson 1960s, played by Paul Dano.
Brian Wilson 1980s, played by John Cusack.
Melinda Ledbetter, played by Elizabeth Banks.
Dr. Eugene Landy, played by Paul Giamatti.
Mike Love, played by Jake Abel.
Dennis Wilson, played by Kenny Wormald.
Love & Mercy is a 2014 American biographical drama film directed by Bill Pohlad about the Beach Boys'
co-founder and leader Brian Wilson and his struggles with mental illness during the 1960s and 1980s.
It stars Paul Dano and John Cusack as the young and older Wilson, respectively, with Elizabeth
Banks as his second wife Melinda Ledbetter and Paul Giamatti as his psychologist Dr.
Eugene Landy.
The title comes from Wilson's 1988 song of the same name.
The film alternates between Wilson's production of the album Pet Sounds (1966) and
his treatment under Landy's 24-hour therapy program in the late 1980s.
Wilson called the film "very factual", despite containing
parts that "weren't actually as factual".
He had little involvement with its making, although
Ledbetter was relied upon for the 1980s portions.
The cast and crew maintained that nothing in the film was a "Hollywood"
embellishment and that everything was intended to be as truthful as possible.
Conversely, Landy's son Evan felt that his father was unfairly portrayed.
Some minor inaccuracies were noted by critics, a number of which relate to the
minimal coverage devoted to Wilson's family and collaborators.
Ledbetter said that Landy's treatment of Wilson "was
even worse" than the film portrays.
Love & Mercy premiered at the 2014 Toronto International Film Festival on September 7,
2014 and was released by Lionsgate and Roadside Attractions on June 5, 2015.
It grossed $28.6 million over a $10 million budget and received positive reviews
from critics, with Dano's performance garnering significant praise.
It was nominated for two Golden Globes: Best Supporting Actor – Motion
Picture (Paul Dano) and Best Original Song ("One Kind of Love").
A soundtrack album that includes the original score by
Atticus Ross was released on August 14, 2015.
The film explores themes of rock 'n' roll, musician,
therapist, biography, recording studio.
The tone is emotional.